[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question is... says...
[SPEAKER_00]: Many modern teachings suggest that beneath our anxious thoughts lies a pure innate heart or a state of natural goodness and we should use this space as a safe refuge from psychological distress.
[SPEAKER_00]: How should a practitioner evaluate the practice of retreating into these positive feelings and what are the limitations of treating this hard space as an ultimate sanctuary?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, obviously, the main kind of issue with this is how do you know that it's inherently good?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever that thing is, that one might be referring to as heart, innate heart or a state of natural goodness, what is your basis for judgment that it is good, that it is factually good?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it... or is it just like a blind belief, just like wishful thinking?
[SPEAKER_00]: You want it to be good,
[SPEAKER_00]: You choose to believe and determine that it is good and therefore you're going to act as if it's... as if that is an objective truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how real it might feel, how real... how positive that experience might be, it's still based on a mere belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have no factual ground, no discernment to know that the mind is inherently pure and so on, and the clean, and it's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no basis for that knowledge, but... which means that the gap between the belief and something that you can see for yourself will never be reduced.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's like, even in the suttas, when Sotāpanna is being described, he's described as somebody who actually has an insight into good as good and bad as bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody who has a direct internal reference point as to why good is good, bad is bad, or why beneficial is beneficial and unbeneficial is unbeneficial.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like Sotāpanna in the suttas, which means up to that point,
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything that's deemed good and bad, it's going to be sort of judged by, on the basis of, you know, common sense, intelligence, authority, external criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you could make some sense, some degree of understanding, you could even say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not going to be penetrated with wisdom, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it's not going to be seen directly, most acutely,
[SPEAKER_00]: Without any kind of intermediary factors, it won't be seen why good is good and bad is bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why things that are good are actually good?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the criteria that can be seen internally regardless of the culture?
[SPEAKER_00]: Regardless of, you know, the upbringing, the society, the current values, the authority, the law, regardless of any of that, is there a thing that a person can see for themselves, something that ties all good things as good and bad things as bad?
[SPEAKER_00]: And as the suttas describe, sotāpati obviously is that criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what ties everything to be good or beneficial and unbeneficial is what kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Influence those actions and results, influence and results those actions have on the mind, on citta, on the actual citta, not on what you might believe is your inherent pure citta and pure heart.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as the suttas would describe, it's like
[SPEAKER_00]: If certain things are lifting the mind up, in terms of removal of avijjā, removal of obstacles, of hindrances, of things that obscure clear seeing, removal of perversions, or at least things that contribute towards reductions of those unwholesome obstructions,
[SPEAKER_00]: That is why those things are beneficial.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is why those things are good.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can see that already, for that type of insight, you need to have, like, knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not just... it cannot just be rooted in believing that deep down inside, you are still good, if your actions, by body, speech and mind, and, consequently, your own, like, level of wisdom, still supports
[SPEAKER_00]: Acts that are rooted in greed, aversion, distraction, means it's just like... You can be saying and believing all you want that inherently you're good, means you kind of carry a view that you can do whatever you want, even if you don't, but that's what you're implying, because the pure heart underneath it all cannot be polluted by these unwholesome actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's completely the opposite view of what the Buddha said the truth is, which is beings are defined by their actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can have the pure heart all you want, if you are... As I said, if your actions by body, speech and mind are still come from greed, aversion, delusion, obviously, you know, the different extents of it, you know, it's not all kind of black and white, some things can be worse, some things can be not as bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, if they still carry the roots of those three unwholesome poisons, as the Buddha referred to them, means you're not good.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not beneficial.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's the actions that you do that define you.
[SPEAKER_00]: They define your states of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: They determine them, what they will be like.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want citta to become truly pure, good, the state of natural goodness, whatever that is, clean up your actions,
[SPEAKER_00]: Develop wisdom in terms of, like, all those mental states that Buddha said you shouldn't be cultivating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Make the effort and don't cultivate them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all the mental states that Buddha said you should cultivate, make the effort and cultivate them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you are purifying the actual heart.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are purifying the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you could rightly claim that, okay, now I am in the state of natural goodness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see, it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't be natural goodness, because natural implies it's kind of always there, regardless of your actions, regardless of your views, regardless of obstructions in everything that you do, and that's simply not the case, because if that were the case, then, well, there is no point, there is no need, there wouldn't have been any need for practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There wouldn't have been any need for the training, the gradual training that the suttas go on and on about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, it would all just boil down to adopting a view that inherently your mind is pure and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing else to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if the mind is pure anyway, like, there is really no reason to train in anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: The point of this is that, yeah, I don't doubt that such views exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: I heard it myself many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, like, if you strip them down to the principles of what those views are based on, you'll see that that's completely the opposite views of what dhamma's views are, or what the views of the dhamma are.
[SPEAKER_00]: What the suttas are, what the training is, the purpose behind, the principles behind, obviously, such views would not be compatible with this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're, like, going in the opposite directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: One says, through training, you can actually develop the purity of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The other one says, no, the mind is already pure, therefore, when things get too much, just remember that belief and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing else you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you do stuff, even if you say, but I keep the precepts and I do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way,
[SPEAKER_00]: The view that the mind is inherently pure makes everything else secondary and redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the mind is pure in and of itself, as a state of natural goodness, so naturally good, not corrupted, then, again, just remember that and you wouldn't have to do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, such views basically dampen the training or certainly remove the weight and the emphasis of the actual self-training.
[SPEAKER_00]: Training of the mind, purification of the actions, and everything the suttas talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you might, like, partially train, but then, if it gets too much, you just convince yourself that you're already pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing else to do anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just remember that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, you could see how it just completely, eh... takes away any purpose behind the effort that you would be investing in training.
[SPEAKER_00]: Training in the principles of the precepts and sense restraint, clear seeing, calming of the citta, and other things the suttas talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's like... it's a bit of a contradiction in terms that somebody who holds a view of innate pure heart, that's always uncorrupted, always pure, calls themselves a practitioner of the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those things are mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're either basically practitioner of the Buddha's teaching, who then recognizes, takes responsibility for the lack of the purity of your mind, for the lack of the development of the mind, and that's the purpose of the training,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or doesn't take the responsibility, because it believes that it's already pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you're not a practitioner, because, like, if it's already pure, there's nothing for you to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it finishes with a question.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what are the limitations of treating this heart space as ultimate sanctuary?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the limitation itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you need a sanctuary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you have not dealt with things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have not understood or freed yourself from dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need a place you can hide from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's not freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not sotāpati.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just basically a coping mechanism.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the limitation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a view that's just used as a coping mechanism and even if you genuinely believe in the training outline, in the suttas, you'll be undermining yourself by not questioning these views and by holding them, they will naturally be taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: A degree of emphasis that is necessary on the training and the aspects of the training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you'll be, like, inadvertently keeping the training at the arm's length.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, if you take the responsibility for the innate heart, whichever way it presents itself, that means you have to give up the idea of a safe space internally until sotāpādī.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why these views are not just like intellect... well, none of the views are just like intellectual kind of decisions.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're all rooted in emotional needs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to train rightly, you need to give up any false refuge and really commit to the training and recognize that the only sure, actual way out of suffering is through taming the animal
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding, penetrating it with wisdom, and then truly understanding that inability, impossibility of ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the true landlock, the sense of not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just something you say as a coping method.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I said, in order to actually come to that point, you would need to re-evaluate all these views of safe space and pure hearts and ultimate realities that you can kind of find your shelter in, while clearly still bothered by the world and worldly winds.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, which means, basically, again, there is no freedom, there is just the need of... for escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why any such view, it's really kind of on the level of pretty much any other religious view that's based on, like, you know, deities and entities and so on as ultimate saviors, ultimate protectors.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that kind of takes it away, takes the weight away from you, puts it on something else and you can run to it when things get too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not freedom, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, certainly not the one that the Buddha was describing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's kind of my point.